{
  "reference_number": "12143",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The previous emissions reductions targets set by our government have lacked ambition and have allowed us to continue to be\n complacent about our contribution to global climate change. We need a firm target, set in legislation, now, so that we can start to\n develop our domestic actions to reach our goal - binding legislation is the best way to get domestic action in motion."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Not only would this place Aotearoa New Zealand as a leader on the world stage in the climate change action space, but it would also\n encourage innovation in the energy sector as we would need to embrace ecological modernisation to achieve this as noted in table 1\n of the discussion document."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Emissions trading schemes and international carbon units do not reduce our emissions as a country. They shift the burden of\n\n emissions reductions to another place, often one that is less developed and less privileged. If we are to achieve environmental and\n climate justice we need to stop shifting our responsibility onto countries in need and instead focus on climate action at home\n through domestic emissions reductions only. However, domestic emissions reductions will also need to take into account justice at\n\n home - as noted in the discussion document, lower income households are most likely to feel the strongest impacts of domestic\n climate action. We need to plan for a just transition from our reliance on fossil fuels and high emissions industry to ensure that we do\n\n not unfairly impact those of lower incomes and the working class who rely on these industries for work."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We need a legally binding and concrete target in order to foster the innovation and societal changes we will need to see in order to\n reach said target."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As emissions budgets can increase predictability for businesses and New Zealanders about what is needed over a shorter-term\n horizon this proposal seems to be in line with the idea of planning for a just transition for those who work in, or are adjacent to,\n industries that rely on fossil fuels and produce high emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "This would allow governments that care less about the climate and the people affected by it to arbitrarily set budgets that could\ndisempower the policies and legislation we hope will be put in place as a result of this bill and the budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, there need to be tangible plans, specific policies and actions designed to be taken confirmed within a certain time frame\n\notherwise we run the risk of another tokenistic target such as our current target, which is not backed up with domestic climate action\nat all."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Consultation must be undertaken with iwi, mana whenua and those who will be significantly impacted by both climate change (aka\ninaction) and by taking domestic climate change action - i.e. lower income households. Workers in industries relying on fossil fuels, or\n\nadjacent to those industries (e.g. hospitality in Taranaki that has a high level of patronage from those within the oil industry) must be\nconsulted on how to achieve a just transition that allows them to maintain their livelihoods through the change to a zero carbon\n\nAotearoa. We should also ensure we pay attention to global environmental and climate injustices when designing our own response\nto climate change - we do not want to, for example, continue to burden developing and Global South countries with the responsibility\n\nfor our emissions under the Emissions Trading Scheme, and have a moral responsibility to take a leadership role on taking climate\naction, because we are capable of doing so."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I do think that the matters that could be taken into account when making decisions as the Climate Change committee (pg 44 of\ndiscussion document) need to be reconsidered to include a more holistic understanding of the impacts of climate change on people\n\nand society. The majority of considerations currently noted in this list are technocratic - economic, fiscal, scientific, technology.... In\nreality a Climate Change Commission must have direct consideration for the four basic wellbeings which include cultural and social as\n\npriorities, and consider the social impacts beyond just those pertaining to fuel poverty - especially the social impacts of inaction and\nthe social and health impacts that our current state contributes to globally."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "In actuality we should be moving away from any reliance on the NZ ETS for emissions reduction. That being said, if it must remain in\n\noperation then the Climate Change Commission should be the decision makers in order to keep this function independent from the\ngovernment if the government, and thus it's priorities in delivering environmental wellbeing for Aotearoa, changes. This would clarify\nand focus the role on reduction of emissions as this would be their key priority."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with much of the proposed expertise but there should also be the inclusion of a human geographer or social scientist. Or\n\nboth."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Particularly with the Local Government Amendment Bill 2018 currently in front of select committee I do not think additional\n\nadministrative or compliance costs should be a barrier for local government and other public services to be better informed and\nprepared for climate change in mitigation. This is for the benefit of all of New Zealand so should not be thought of simply in financial\n\nterms. Voluntary reporting rarely works so this should be a legislative requirement."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need a tangible plan for a just transition for workers. The working class and lower income households will be impacted by\n\nwhatever action we take next - whether that be not enough action resulting in increased climate change impacting their jobs and\nability to work, or increased domestic action increasing pricing for various services and products utilised by these classes. We need\n\nto explicitly address this if we are to seriously achieve a move towards a zero carbon Aotearoa."
    }
  ]
}
